Hey, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ל"ה Lamed Hey
and we're in the middle of a
סוגיא sugya in ש"ס Shas on בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot although there's
another גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim that leads ראשונים Rishonim to radically,
some ראשונים Rishonim to radically reassess this גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, this גמרא
Gemara has said that the period of בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot is
from the time the sun sets until the sky darkens. There's a
little bit of a question about maybe even a few, a few
minutes after sunset it's still day as long as the sky is
red. So it has a difference between these two positions of two-thirds
of a מיל mil and three-quarters of a מיל mil based on
whether it starts immediately after the sun sets or once, or after
the red goes away.
And we will get back to this בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot in
a minute. The גמרא Gemara first is going to digress a little
bit. So when it gets back we will sort of fully, more
fully lay out the different opinions. So let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara from three lines, two lines from
the
top, middle of the line, וחילופא בחלסא. v'hilufa b'khalsa. So the debate
that we just had here of
which was
שמואל Shmuel says three חלקי מיל chelkei mil
and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says two חלקי מיל, chelkei mil, which
was three-quarters and two-thirds. So the reverse opinion is held by this
חלסא khalsa which is this like big type of a basket. And
that's not really the reverse, but the point is that one here
says two and the other says three and the two and three
numbers switch over there. דאמר רבה חלסא בת תרי כורי שרי לטלטולי
ובת תלתא כורי אסר לטלטולי D'amar Rabbah khalsa bat tarei kurei shar
lei letaltulei u'vat tlata kurei asar lei letaltulei because רבה Rabbah says
חלסא בת תרי כורי שרי לטלטולי ובת תלתא כורי אסר לטלטולי. khalsa
bat tarei kurei shar lei letaltulei u'vat tlata kurei asar lei letaltulei.
If you have this like big wicker basket or whatever type of
basket it is, then it's the size of two כור, kor, כור
kor is a very large dry volume measure, then you can carry
it on שבת. Shabbos. It's not מוקצה, muktzah, it's still considered a
vessel. But if it is three כור kor large, you know, imagine
like we're getting to the huge sizes like something let's say the
size of a refrigerator, maybe not that big, but very, very large,
then you cannot carry it on שבת Shabbos because then it's מוקצה,
muktzah, then it's not considered a vessel. And there's similar discussions about
at what stage is it a vessel to be able to become
טמא tamei or not as well. Here it's a question about carrying
it on שבת. Shabbos. רב יוסף אמר בת תלתא כורי נמי שרי
בת ארבעה כורי אסור. Rav Yosef amar bat tlata kurei nami shari
bat arba kurei assur.
Three כור kor is you can also move it, it's still a
vessel. Bat ארבעה כורי, arba kurei, four כור, kor, it is forbidden.
Okay, so there you have, so what do you have? So you
have רבה Rabbah saying two and רב יוסף Rav Yosef saying three.
And that's somewhat parallel here because רבה Rabbah said in the name
of שמואל Shmuel three, or reverses, three-quarters of a מיל. mil. So
here he says two. There by the vessel he says two. And
רב יוסף Rav Yosef says in the name of
שמואל Shmuel two, two-thirds of a מיל mil and here he says
three, three-quarters. So two and three reverse themselves. Obviously very different הלכות,
halachos, no logical correspondence, just a good way of remembering it. Okay,
I said, I think I said incorrectly before about it being רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda and שמואל. Shmuel. No, they're both saying statements in
the name of רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, but
one is said by the name of רבה, Rabbah, one is said
by רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, and they have different opinions. So here,
rather than being רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל,
Shmuel, they themselves have these positions of two and three, but they
are reversed and in a totally different context. אמר אביי בעי מיני
דמר בשעת מעשה. Amar Abaye ba'ei minei d'mar b'shat ma'aseh. So said
אביי, Abaye, בעי מיני דמר בשעת מעשה, ba'ei minei d'mar b'shat ma'aseh,
I asked the master, meaning
רבה, Rabbah, בשעת מעשה b'shat ma'aseh when the case actually occurred. I
had this huge basket and I wanted to move it and רבה
Rabbah was the more strict opinion. He said two, yes, three, no.
I asked him in a real case ואפילו בת תרי כורי לא
שרי ליה v'afillu bat tarei kurei lo shar lei and he didn't
even allow two כור. kor. He was being very strict. Okay, כמאן
כי האי תנא, keman ki hai tanna,
like the following תנא. tanna. Who is this going like? דתנינא במשנה
D'tneina b'mishna we taught in a משנה, mishna, כוורת הקש kiveret hakash
if you have this type of literally כוורת kiveret literally means like
a beehive but again some type of a wicker
basket, וכוורת הקנים v'kiveret hakanim or made out of reeds,
ובור וספינה אלכסנדרית u'bor v'sfinah Alexandrit and the well but it means
like the water cistern of a ספינה אלכסנדרית, sfinah Alexandrit, an Alexandrian
boat. I don't know what the significance of Alexandrian is, I'm sure
some Sattino will say, I mean what's his name Steinsaltz will say,
but anyway they would have a big, a big well, water cistern
of a freshwater of sweet water that they would take with them
on boats, right? Because they would have a good water supply, you
can't drink water, water everywhere not a drop to drink, you can't
drink from the water of the ocean. So these are huge, imagine
you had a boat, imagine the size that you would have to
fill up of, you know, of a water cistern in order to
take for a whole journey. So these are like huge vessels. So
these types of things, אף על פי, af al pi, take out
the אף על פי af al pi because it's not אף על
פי, af al pi, it's because שיש להם שוליים she'yesh lahem shulayim
they have, they have a floor, so you might say there's a
vessel, they're a container, ואין
מחזיקות מ' סאה בלח שהן כוריים ביבש, v'ein machzikot mem se'ah blach
she'hein korayim b'yavesh, but if they contain מ' סאה, mem se'ah, 40
סאה se'ah of liquid measure, which is the size of a מקוה,
mikvah, the minimum size of a מקוה, mikvah, so it's actually not
as big, you know, these might be very large, but actually think
about it, the size of a מקוה, mikvah, I mean we have
big מקואות, mikvaos, but the minimum size is enough to fully immerse
a person in. So it's basically like the size of a bathtub.
Okay, in terms of how big of a container it is. It's
not huge, okay, I mean, it's not small, but okay, it's a
size for a person that basically contain the water for a person
to immerse in, which is כוריים ביבש, korayim beyavesh, which is two
כור kor dry measure. So those things טהורים tehorim are טהור tahor
because they're not considered vessels. So therefore they cannot become טמא. tamei.
So therefore רבה Rabba would not even if it were two כור
kor would not allow it, although his initial teaching was two כור,
kor, so that's consistent with this, yeah, maybe it sounds right. If
that's consistent with this משנה Mishna that says even once it hits
two כור, kor, it is no longer considered a vessel and therefore
you can't move it on שבת. Shabbos. Now I should just say,
it's not so obvious why you can't move a vessel on שבת
Shabbos or why we should exactly a non-vessel on שבת Shabbos or
why we should exactly apply the same definitions of טומאה tumah to
vessels, but this is sometimes what you do see which is that
we apply a you know sort of a category across הלכה halakha
across you know
we sort of apply definitions across categories even though maybe logically each
category should have its own definition. Okay, so we're worried about that
more when we get to a more focused discussion of מוקצה, muktzeh,
although we are already starting to see and we've seen before מוקצה
muktzeh finds its way into many many different discussions, just gets touched
on and you know move on, touched on and move on. So
really like מוקצה muktzeh is spread throughout the ש"ס. Shas. But there
are some סוגיות sugyot which are more focused on that so we
will not we will not overly focus on it right now.
Okay, the Alexandrian ship is just a large ship that doesn't just
sail in rivers or along the shore but across the sea. I
see.
I see. So it actually crosses seas, so you have to lean
a lot more water. Right. Exactly. Very good. Okay, so that's the
Alexandrian ship. Okay, so אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, שמע
מינה האי גודשא תילתא הוי. shma mina hai gudesha tilsa havei. So
we see that the the heaping is a third. What does that
mean? What because before we gave two measures, we gave a dry
measure and a liquid measure. Why do you need two measures? Isn't
one enough? So the point is no, because when you have a
dry measure you get the amount that heaps over the edge of
the vessel, right, I mean by liquid you mean there's a small
amount because of the water surface, the meniscus I think no, that's
the thing that goes on, anyway the water surface, the amount of
liquid can slightly exceed the height of the vessel, right, but by
by a dry measure if you're let's say having grain, right, so
you can have a but no but actually but depending if you
heap it, if you heap, right, you can get a lot more.
Okay, and רש"י Rashi says particularly if this is very wide and
not so high you can get a lot that you add by
dry measure in the heap, a big mount. So anyway, so אביי
Abaye says so of course everybody knows exactly the volume measure of
מ' סאה mem se'ah in liquid and two כור kor in dry,
so and of course the two כור kor is a third more,
so that's what אביי Abaye says, I don't know the math but
anyway, זו האי גודשא, zu hai gudesha, this heaping is תילתא הוי
tilsa havei is one third more than because of the dry measure
you get one third more than in the liquid measure because of
the heaping and that is the way the degree to which this
two כור kor of dry exceeds the forty סאה se'ah of liquid.
Okay, now back to, that was all digression, back to בין השמשות.
Bein Hashmashos. So until now we've been talking about the sky getting
red and darkening and בין השמשות Bein Hashmashos starts at sunset, maybe
according to a different version of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אמר שמואל,
amar Shmuel, of of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, it starts after the you know
after the redness goes away, that also and that's the way that
the גמרא Gemara presumably explained the debate between who was it?
One minute. Right, רבה ורב יוסף, Rabba veRav Yosef, thank you. No,
רבה ורב יוסף Rabba veRav Yosef I know but it was also
the way the גמרא Gemara explained the difference between the two תנאים,
Tannaim, right? Wasn't it?
Between
excuse me, no,
between oh no it was two ways of explaining רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, I'm sorry, right, it was the two versions of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda about whether רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's בין השמשות Bein Hashmashos
starts at sunset or after the sky grows red. Okay, and it
goes for two thirds or three quarters of a מיל. mil. So
a מיל mil there's a debate in the ראשונים Rishonim based on
the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim how long it takes to walk
a מיל, mil, anywhere between 18 and 24 minutes, there's a middle
position 22 and a half, we won't worry about that. So if
you do three quarters of a מיל mil everybody agrees let's put
it this way, everybody agrees these two versions of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda both agree that צאת tzais is three quarters of a מיל
mil after sunset. The only question is whether בין השמשות Bein Hashmashos
begins at sunset or a few minutes later, but everybody agrees that
צאת tzais is three quarters of a מיל mil after sunset. So
what's three quarters of 18? It's about 13 and three quarters, let's
say 14 rounded, three quarters of 24 is 18. So everybody agrees
even if you take the latest position three quarters of a מיל
mil times 24 is 18 minutes after sunset is צאת, tzais, so
many of you realize actually our צאת tzais is much later than
18 minutes after sunset, we'll discuss that but that's where we are
right now, anywhere between 14. Anywhere between fourteen to eighteen minutes, and
it starts at sunset or maybe a few minutes after. Okay, so
now let's see as the גמרא Gemara continues. אביי חזייה לרבא Abayei
chazyei leRava דקא חדווי למערב. dekahadvi lema'arav. אביי Abayei saw רבא Rava
that he was peering towards the west after sunset to see what
color the sky was. Now if you remember, we said that the
east stops being red and grows dark and then the top grows
dark. So here רבא Rava is looking towards the west, so what's
that about? אמר ליה, Amar lei, so אביי Abayei said to him,
עד דתניא כל זמן שפני מזרח מאדימין, Ad hatanya kol zman shepenei
mizrach maadimin, don't we say that the- one of the stages is
as long as the face of the east is red? So it's
the east that's red that determines one of the stages of becoming
night. What are you doing looking at the west? אמר ליה, Amar
lei, he said to him, מי סברת פני מזרח ממש? Mi savart
penei mizrach mamash? No,
you think it means literally the face of the east? That's not
what it means. פנים המאדימין את המזרח. Panim hamaadimim es hamizrach. It
means the side of the sky that causes the east to get
red, which means the west, which is a pretty funny way of
saying it, but actually it makes a big difference because, right, the
eastern sky grows dark a lot faster than the western sky because
the sun is setting in the western sky. So if he is
looking here at the western sky and the red of that sky
has to go away, that means that the צאת tzeis will presumably
come later.
So איכא דאמרי, Ik d'amri, some say רבא חזייה לאביי, Rava chazyei
le'Abayei, it was the reverse, רבא Rava saw אביי Abayei דקא חדווי
למזרח, dekahadvi lemizrach, he was looking at the east, but אביי, Abayei,
he was looking at the east. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבא
Rava said, מי סברת פני מזרח ממש? Mi savart penei mizrach mamash?
You think it literally means no, the east? לא, Lo, no. פנים
המאדימין את המזרח. Panim hamaadimim es hamizrach.
It means the side of the sky that makes the east red,
which is the west.
וסימנך כוותא, Vesimanach kivsa, it's like a window that if you have
a window, the light comes from behind the window and shines on
the opposite wall. So what we were really talking about when we
said פני מזרח penei mizrach is the face opposite the east, which
is the west. Now it's a little strange here, who cares about
the red? Right? Because we should have said when the top gets
dark. And
now first of all I don't know, I should have checked, but
does the top of the sky grow darker faster than the eastern
sky, than the western sky? Is the western sky the last part
of the sky to get dark? I assume it is because the
sun sets in the west, right? So what becomes strange here is
that if we're talking about the redness goes out of the west,
that's later than the top becoming dark. And in the- in the
ברייתא brita it was first the sky stops being red and then
it grows dark. So I'm not exactly sure right how to read
this about the western sky. What's also not clear is who cares
about the redness? At the end of the day it's not צאת
tzeis until the sky grows dark; the red just is an intermediate
stage. So this is not clear why this matters so much. There
is a very long תשובה, teshuva, look, there's a lot been written
about בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, but there's a very long תשובה teshuva
by the מהרם אלשקאר Maharam Alshakar that he- מהרם אלשקאר, Maharam Alshakar,
I forget I think it's fifteenth, maybe sixteenth century, I forget the
biography. Anyway, very, very long תשובה teshuva where not only does he
work through the גמרות, Gemaros, which everybody does, but he actually looks
first of all at the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and brings that in the
conversation and also very much talks about the sort of the reality
of the sky and how that fits in. Okay, but this is
a problematic גמרא, Gemara, A, because how do you have the redness
going away from the west before the
sky- before the top of the sky gets dark since that happens-
since if it's the west, the west gets dark the latest? And
number two, why does this stage matter? It only matters according to
the version that it's still day while it's red. But that doesn't-
in practice we seem to reject that version. We say as soon
as the sun sets, it's already בין השמשות bein hashmashos until the
sky gets dark, and we've now said that's three-quarters of a מיל.
mil. Everybody agrees that's after sunset. So right now whatever you do
with this גמרא, Gemara, we are saying that בין השמשות bein hashmashos
is fourteen to eighteen minutes after sunset. Most common opinions would have
a מיל mil as eighteen minutes, so we'd have- I mean not
בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, so we'd have בין השמשות bein hashmashos from
sunset for fourteen minutes and then צאת. tzeis. Yes, David.
How are you defining dark? Meaning you asked the question does the
sky above grow dark? Are you still- is there still some red
in the horizon?
Yeah. Well that's the point is I don't know how I'm defining
it, but the point is still the top of the sky gets
darker before the western horizon- before the western horizon, right. I think
so. So the problem is that the משנה Mishnah says the red
goes out of the פני מזרח penei mizrach and then the sky
gets dark. So if פני מזרח penei mizrach means the western horizon,
then the order is reversed.
So just about the three stars coming out-
we haven't mentioned three stars. We're going to mention that.
You were talking about that definition of dark?
Yes, but- but we haven't mentioned that. Right now we've just talked
about the redness going out of the sky and the sky becoming
dark, and we've actually given a number to it, which is helpful,
but that gets us fourteen minutes, so maybe eighteen. So the question
is how do we get our number? So I will give you
a quick answer to that because none of that is in our
גמרא. Gemara. That is based on a contradiction between this גמרא Gemara
and the גמרא Gemara in פסחים. Pesachim. The גמרא Gemara in פסחים...
Pesachim... and that דף צד Daf Tzaddi Daled basically says, which is
one of the places that we learn how long it takes to
walk a מיל mil based on the different versions of that גמרא,
Gemara, it says that from the time the morning star comes out
until sunrise is four מיל, mil, עלות השחר alos hashachar until sunrise
is four מיל, mil, and similarly from sunset until צאת הכוכבים tzeis
hakochavim is four מיל. mil. Now, four מיל mil is 72 minutes,
so if you write four times 18, you might have heard of
שיטת רבינו תם, shittas Rabbeinu Tam, which is 72 minutes after sunset.
That's because that גמרא Gemara says until the stars come out is
four מיל. mil. Now how do you reconcile these גמרות? Gemaras? So
the simplest answer, you know, anyway, number one, there's always a question
of which גמרא Gemara do you treat as your sort of real
one and which one do you somehow explain away somewhere. So the
גאונים, Geonim, and followed by them the הגרא, the Gra, that's a
big jump of about a thousand years or so, but anyway, basically
take the approach which is the approach normally taken, which is you
give more weight to the גמרא Gemara that's about the real discussion,
the primary locus of the discussion. Here we're in שבת, Shabbos, we're
devoting a whole page or more to discussing בין השמשות. bein hashmashos.
This גמרא Gemara rules, and therefore this גמרא, Gemara, the you know,
the time it gave is three quarters of a מיל, mil, that's
when צאת tzeis is. End of story. What about that's the only
time the גמרא, Gemara, it's going to talk about the stars, but
the only quantifiable time is three quarters of a מיל, mil, that's
what's what. What's the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim talking about? So
the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim is not talking about when halachically
it's defined as night. The גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim is talking
about for its various reasons, it's asking an astronomical question of how
thick is the רקיע. rakia. Because the גמרא's Gemara's understanding about how
it, how the works is, you have a, can I borrow this
just because it's flexible, for a second here, is, okay, this is
the רקיע rakia is a dome over the, over the earth here.
Okay, the sun rises in the east, well, I don't know if
it's east, rises in the east, sets in the west, then as
it's getting, as it sets, it goes through the thickness, there's a
window in the רקיע rakia at here, goes through the thickness, the
reason there's still some light coming out is because the sun is
in this like tunnel, essentially through the thickness of the רקיע, rakia,
call it a window but like a tunnel, and therefore you're still
seeing some light after sunset. Then after it gets to the other
end of the tunnel, it starts rising up here, and at night
it goes from west to east, this is opaque, and therefore you
stop seeing any redness once it's fully exits the tunnel and starts
its reverse journey. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara wants to know how
thick is the רקיע. rakia. How long does it take the sun
to pass through the thickness of that tunnel? So it assumes that
in the morning the sun starts passing through the thickness of the
tunnel when the first star is, the morning star is seen, because
that's when there's the first bit of light, right? Until it passes
all the way through the tunnel and it's sunrise, that's four מיל
mil from the little bit of light till sunrise. Here too, from
the time the sun sets till there's no light. But the גמרא
Gemara describes the time as the stars come out. So what the
הגרא the Gra says is, is that it's the stars, not three
stars. Three stars is, first of all, we haven't even mentioned stars
here. We're going to see stars when we turn the page. But
there it says three medium-sized stars, not the stars you see late
at night, but stars that you see like small, like that you
see at the beginning of the evening and so on. So, so
the הגרא the Gra says over there we're not talking about three
stars. We're talking about all the stars. We want to know about
the thickness of the רקיע, rakia, and the גמרא Gemara assumes the
same way after sunset the sun is passing through this tunnel, the
stars are scattered throughout the thickness of the רקיע. rakia. And the
reason as it gets darker later at night you see more stars
is because more stars descend, right? They also descend at an, at
an even rate through the thickness. So the stars that are at
the very edge of the thickness will come out only right at
the end. You understand, you get the, you get the idea here?
So after the, the thickness of the רקיע, rakia, all the stars
are seen because there's time for all the stars to descend. And
that's why it takes four מיל, mil, the same time it takes
the sun to move through the thickness of the רקיע. rakia. That's
how the הגרא the Gra explains it, which basically means don't worry
about the גמרא Gemara in פסחים. Pesachim. Okay, this is גמרא, Gemara,
three quarters of a מיל mil after sunset is, is צאת, tzeis,
14 to 18 minutes. That's the הגרא. the Gra. Comes along רבינו
תם, Rabbeinu Tam, way before the הגרא the Gra but after the
גאונים, Geonim, and he says no, no, no, the גמרא Gemara in
פסחים Pesachim is the real גמרא. Gemara. צאת tzeis is not till
72 minutes after sunset. What about this גמרא Gemara that says three
quarters, two thirds of a מיל, mil, whatever? That's talking about how
much time does בין השמשות bein hashmashos start
before 72 minutes? So move back from 72 minutes, 14 minutes, 18
minutes, that's בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. And the first hour after sunset
is totally day. So according to רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, you basically
have 58 minutes after sunset Friday afternoon where you can totally do
מלאכה, melacha, totally day. And only starting from minute 58 to minute
72, that's בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. And this גמרא Gemara actually does
not mean 15 minutes, 14 minutes after visible sunset, it means 14
minutes before the end of. end of the sun going through this
tunnel. And that really 58 minutes of day, 14 minutes of בין
השמשות Bein Hashmashos at the end of the 72. So, what is
motivating רבינו תם? Rabbeinu Tam? It's been pointed out that in France
where רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam lived, it gets dark very very late.
And there is no way you could say that 14, 18 minutes
after sunset is the darkness the גמרא Gemara is talking about. So
he had to basically that influences his understanding about when it was
and led to when this is a normal way of explaining where
רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, you know, what led to such an explanation
where
and that רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam doesn't say this but, you know,
but it's consistent with where it is and anyway he says that's
why it's these 72 minutes. A lot of ראשונים Rishonim that it
only says after that, a lot of ראשונים Rishonim agree with רבינו
תם. Rabbeinu Tam. A lot of ראשונים Rishonim were living in France
and Germany where it gets late, where it gets dark very late.
So some were living in Spain too. Also, anyway, so there we
don't we don't do either, right? Most say 45 minutes, something like
that, 42 minutes. It's not רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam 72, it's not
הגר״א's the Gra 14. Where do we get this from?
So there's a third opinion out there which is basically like, look,
let's not this is basically what רבינו יונה Rabbeinu Yonah in ברכות
Berachos says. Let's not try to figure out the, you know, the
thickness of the רקיע, Rakia, four מיל, mil, three-quarters of a מיל,
mil, there's these contradictory גמרות. Gemaras. Let's not, you know, let's not
worry about that. Let's just go by the גמרא Gemara about stars.
And let's actually do something radical, which is, let's go out and
look outside and see when you can see three stars, okay? And
when you can see, so there's this opinion basically says forget this
contradiction, we're not going to resolve it, but when there are stars
that appear all over, all throughout the sky, then you definitely have
the three medium-sized stars the גמרא Gemara is going to refer to,
it hasn't yet, and that's okay, and then based on, you know,
various like, you know, astronomical, whatever,
measures, they come up with this number 42 or 45, some say
a little, whatever, somewhere in that range, that's the basic position we
go to which isn't either. Now, some would like to say that
the 42, 45 can work according to some of these variations because
this is the question: do any of these numbers, or let's say
the 14 and the 72 number, are they fixed or do they
depend on where you are in terms of, you know, latitude? Because
they should. The darkness is a big factor of that. So הגר״א
the Gra says explicitly his number does depend on latitude. And if
you're in a place where it gets darker later, it's not going
to be 14 minutes. In ארץ ישראל, Israel, right, which is where
the these סוגיות Sugyas originated, I mean the גמרא Gemara is בבלי,
Bavli, but it gets dark very quickly. And in ארץ ישראל Israel
in ירושלים Yerushalayim they follow מנהג הגר״א, Minhag Hagra, they don't say
14 minutes, they don't say 18, they add a few minutes, but
they say 25. But at least in ירושלים Yerushalayim 25 minutes after
שקיעה Shkiyah is considered צאת, Tzeis, okay? For מוצאי שבת. Motzoei Shabbos.
But even if you're a הגר״א Gra person, if you're higher up
on the globe or lower down, the latitude is not at the
equator, that number will change. It probably won't get to be as
late as 45 minutes, but the number will certainly change and also
change based on season. רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein says the
same is true with הגר״א the Gra and with רבינו תם. Rabbeinu
Tam. And he tries to argue that רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam 72
minutes adjusted for latitude in America becomes 45 minutes.
Now the problem with that is is that if the 72 minutes
were were true in in France, then you could say yeah, so
France's 72 is America's 45. But רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam is ostensibly
explaining a גמרא Gemara that's dealing with the realities in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and בבל, Bavel, and there's no way to say that
that 72 becomes a 45 in America. But that's רב משה's Rav
Moshe position. רב משה Rav Moshe would like to believe that all
of us who do some 42 to 45 minutes are doing a
modified רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. Okay, but most, more what we're doing
is a straight observation of stars. Okay? And you do have הגר״א
the Gra and רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, which are הגר״א the Gra
is much less, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam is much more. Although if
it's modified for location, הגר״א the Gra would probably be a little
bit closer to what we are. So that's all the basic range
of positions. None of that is in this גמרא. Gemara. This גמרא
Gemara is very straightforward, three-quarters of a מיל Mil after sunset, which
would give you 14 minutes, maybe adjusted for location, okay? But a
lot of that has to do with reconciling it with the גמרא
Gemara in פסחים. Pesachim. Okay, so that was a little very quick
distillation of the positions of בין השמשות. Bein Hashmashos. Yes?
I thought you said the what was motivating רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
was where he lived, so isn't he trying to explain it based
on where he lived and not?
No, I said subconsciously, meaning if you look around and you see
that it's light out for an hour after sunset, how could the
גמרא Gemara mean 14 minutes it's already צאת? Tzeis? Okay? But I
you know, if רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam were aware about the differences
between ארץ ישראל, Israel, you know, when did it get stars, he
might have said, 'Oh, no, it's fine, the גמרא Gemara means ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, we're different where whatever.' But, you know, he just
said the גמרא Gemara itself meant four מיל mil after sunset, and
he explained it by פסחים. Pesachim. Again, that's speculation. I'm not the
first one to say that. I mean, it's commonly explained that that
influenced רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. perception of that. But nevertheless, it is
a major שיטה shita of the ראשונים, Rishonim, widely held by the
ראשונים, Rishonim, who all lived in these lands. But anyway, widely held
that גמרא Gemara that says it's 72 minutes. Yes.
The ראשונים Rishonim who held that way, did they travel much? For
instance, how did the ראש, Rosh,
who went from Germany to Spain, which would have a bit...
bit closer to the equator? It's a good... Look, even the ראשונים
Rishonim in Spain, the רמב"ן Ramban is a big supporter of רבנו
תם Rabbenu Tam and he lived in
Spain. And the מחבר Mechaber who lived in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Right, that's a very good point. The מחבר Mechaber actually rules רבנו
תם, Rabbenu Tam, which shows how much once something like also becomes
a שיטה, shita, you know, then the power of that position may
be, you know, just takes on a life of its own. And
it actually is true that the מחבר Mechaber actually rules like רבנו
תם Rabbenu Tam even לקולא, l'kula, that up to like 58 minutes
after sunset it's still day, which is like crazy. Like, I don't
know anybody who
relies on that today. רבנו תם Rabbenu Tam basically is held לחומרא.
l'chumra. Okay, let's go on now in the גמרא. Gemara. One last
question.
Were there any ראשונים Rishonim in England who...
Yeah, there are a few ראשונים, Rishonim, תוספות Tosafot and אשכנז, Ashkenaz,
but they were very few and yeah, not that I know of.
Good question.
להלכה, L'halacha, if you need to, you can rely on רבנו תם
Rabbenu Tam לקולא? l'kula?
No. I would never do that, because if every single שבת Shabbos
you are doing מלאכה melacha after 45 minutes, you're basically saying I
am prepared to be מחלל שבת m'chalel Shabbos according to רבנו תם,
Rabbenu Tam, I so do not, am not חושש choshesh for that
position.
Like traveling in...
I understand the question and I've given you my answer. My answer
is that if every single שבת Shabbos you are being מחלל שבת
m'chalel Shabbos according to רבנו תם Rabbenu Tam and you don't care
because you're basically rejecting that position, I don't see how בשעת הדחק
b'sha'at hadechak you can say, oh, now I'll decide that I'll rely
on רבנו תם Rabbenu Tam to be מחלל שבת m'chalel Shabbos according
to everybody else. You know, to me it's just,
I see it as inconceivable. If you can get something down to
דרבנן, d'rabbanan, with which a little effort you usually can, that's a
different conversation. But to rely on רבנו תם Rabbenu Tam לקולא l'kula
after sunset, look, the other thing also that's influencing me is I
have, you know, really no question, although there's a whole אלו ואלו
Elu v'Elu etc., if there's very little question in my mind what
the פשט pshat of the גמרא Gemara is, you know, that sunset
is when בין השמשות bein hashmashot begins. So if you want a
better answer, if you want a more lenient answer for that, I
would advise you not to have me on your speed dial when
you're caught in the Holland Tunnel. Okay. רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia אומר
omer כדי שיהלך אדם משתשקע החמה חצי מיל. k'dei she'halech adam mishetishka
hachama chatzi mil. So,
now רבי נחמיה's Rabbi Nechemia position which is not three quarters of
a מיל, mil, but the time it takes to walk from sunset
a half of a מיל. mil. Okay, which would be nine minutes,
let's say. אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chanina, הרוצה לידע שיעורו של
רבי נחמיה, harotze lada'at shiuro shel Rabbi Nechemia, if you want to
know the amount of time of רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia, יניח חמה
בראש הכרמל, yaniach chama b'rosh hacarmel, you leave the sun when it's
at the top of Mount Carmel, וירד ויטבול בים, v'yered v'yitbol bayam,
and go down into the Mediterranean and go, you know, be טובל,
tovel,
ויעלה v'ya'ale and get back up to the top of Mount Carmel,
can't be too tall of a mountain, וזהו שיעורו של רבי נחמיה,
v'zehu shiuro shel Rabbi Nechemia, that's the שיעור shiur of רבי נחמיה.
Rabbi Nechemia. Now what does this mean? So רש"י Rashi says it
means that's the half of the מיל, mil, that's the nine minutes.
Of course it's got to be go
down a mountain, טובל, tovel, and get back up.
Yeah, well טובל tovel doesn't take time. But yeah, it's got to
be a pretty short mountain. So maybe ירד yered doesn't mean the
sun is בראש כרמל, b'rosh carmel, maybe you're ירד yered from I
don't know where you're ירד yered from. Maybe you're not being ירד
yered from בראש כרמל. b'rosh carmel. Is Mount Carmel by the Mediterranean?
Where is Mount Carmel?
It's Haifa. By Haifa, so it is by the Mediterranean. Anyway, so
yeah, maybe it means you're at, maybe it means that you're somewhere,
you know, I don't know, maybe there was an obvious place people
would go down to, that's what there were the kabinas, no what
are those called,
cabanas, that's where the cabanas would be, I don't know. Anyway, it's
hard to know how that gets to be nine minutes. How that
gets,
it's also hard to know why we're saying, why we're giving this
as a weird שיעור, shiur, the time it takes to go go
to the מקוה. mikvah. So תוספות Tosafot says we don't mean the
nine minutes from sunset. What we mean is, if the mountain is
at the top of
הר כרמל, Har Carmel, the sun is at the top of הר
כרמל, Har Carmel, the time it takes you to go down, go
to the מקוה, mikvah, and come back up, that is then you'll
know it's already sunset. Okay, so that's the time from the mountain
at the top of הר כרמל Har Carmel to set. And that's
why it gives the example of going to the מקוה, mikvah, because
here you are, you're a כהן, kohen, you want to eat תרומה
terumah at night, you want to know that you've gone to the
מקוה mikvah before sunset. Even so, it's not clear why it says
go back up. First of all, it just to know that it
was a good טבילה, tvilah, you don't have to go back up.
Okay, and second of all going back up takes time, unless ויעלה
v'ya'ale means to be עולה oleh from the
טבילה tvilah and not to actually and not to actually go back
up the mountain. Okay, but this is a somewhat, you know, it's
a challenging גמרא Gemara exactly what exactly why it's giving this as
an example. All right, so anyway the גמרא Gemara continues, וזהו שיעורו
של רבי נחמיה. v'zehu shiuro shel Rabbi Nechemia.
אמר רבי חייא, Amar Rabbi Chiya, הרוצה לראות בארה של מרים, harotze
lir'ot be'era shel Miriam, now that we're talking about how you sort
of see things and you know, so, so... You said you want
to see the שובשא דנחמי. shuvsha de-nachamei. If you want to see
the well of Miriam that came with בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael throughout
the travels of the wilderness, יעלה לראש הכרמל, Yaaleh lerosh HaCarmel, similar
idea, go to the top of הר כרמל. Har Carmel. Here we
say you go up, before we didn't say you were you went
to the top of the mountain. You go to the top of
the mountain ויצפה ויראה כמין כברה בים veyitzpeh veyireh kemin kivra beyam
and you should peer and you will be able to see something
that looks like some type of a sieve in the sea, וזו
היא בארה של מרים, vezo hi be'erah shel Miriam, and that is
where the well of Miriam is sort of hovering or, you know,
being is
hidden. אמר רב מים המיטלטלין טהור. Amar Rav mayim hamitaltelin tahor. We
have a teaching that a moving well is טהור. tahor. Now what
type of well moves? I mean you can move, you know, a
bucket, you don't move a well. So a moving well is טהור
tahor and that means A, it doesn't become טמא tamei and B,
it even means that it serves as a מקוה. mikvah. So what
is this moving well? זו בארה של מרים. zo be'erah shel Miriam.
This is the well of Miriam that moved miraculously with them through
the desert. Okay. Another...
what do you mean by that then? Yeah we don't know yet.
Okay so... every source says the כנרת. Kinneret. It should be interesting
because from Carmel you might it might look like a sieve, I
don't know. Really?
You said that the גמרא Gemara is but the ים yam refers
to the כנרת Kinneret here?
No, he said רב חיים ויטאל Rav Chaim Vital said the כנרת
Kinneret is to drink from any just drink from בארה של מרים
be'erah shel Miriam was in the כנרת. Kinneret. That's impressive. Okay but
what does the... I have no idea. אמר רב יהודה... Amar Rav
Yehuda... What?
The stream of water that will come from the הר הבית Har
HaBayit to the... from the... yeah in the... that is בארה של
מרים. be'erah shel Miriam. It is מתגלגל mitgalgel and there are people
who have a custom when they make הבדלה Havdalah to drink water...
Oh well the drinking water has to do with another גמרא Gemara
about the רשעים resha'im that were judged on... Oh plus it's moving
around. Okay. I am not fully... exactly. All right, I am not
fully
up
on all the מדרשים Midrashim about בארה של מרים. be'erah shel Miriam.
I already have my benchers...
Okay, okay, fine, you've got me there. All right, אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel. Yes, I understand. בין השמשות.
Bein Hashmashot. All right. All right, so back to the figuring out
the nuts and bolts of בין השמשות. Bein Hashmashot. בין השמשות דרבי
יהודה כהנים טובלים בו. Bein Hashmashot de-Rabbi Yehuda kohanim tovlin bo. So
during the בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which
is again from sunset till two-thirds, three-quarters of a mil, the כהנים
kohanim can go to the מקוה. mikvah. Now why is that? כהנים
kohanim could only go to the מקוה mikvah while it's definitely day.
So the גמרא Gemara says... so let's take a look. למי, Lema'i,
according to... אילימא לרבי יהודה ספיקא. Ilima le-Rabbi Yehuda sefeika. According to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda he can't go during בין השמשות, Bein Hashmashot,
it might already be night. אלא בין השמשות דרבי יהודה לרבי יוסי
כהנים טובלים בו. Ela bein hashmashot de-Rabbi Yehuda le-Rabbi Yossi kohanim tovlin
bo. According in רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot for
רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi perspective, כהנים טובלים בו, kohanim tovlin bo, the
כהנים kohanim can go to the מקוה mikvah because remember רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi said בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot is like the blinking of
an eye. Very nice, tell me בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot is a
blinking of an eye, when? What is that moment when day stops
and night begins? When is that blinking of the eye? So here
we're saying the blinking of the eye of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
is at the end of רבי יהודה's. Rabbi Yehuda Everybody agrees that
night begins three-quarter... well not everybody, we had a בין השמשות Bein
Hashmashot of a half a mil, but between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, night begins three-quarters of a mil after
sunset. Again let's say 14 minutes. The difference is the following, that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says from sunset till 14 minutes is בין
השמשות. Bein Hashmashot. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says those 14 minutes are
day. It's at that end of that 14 minutes in the blink
of an eye it changes from day to night. בין השמשות Bein
Hashmashot lasts for a split second. So during according to רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yossi, this is a חידוש chiddush now, according to רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda period, the sunset till 14
minutes, is definite day and כהנים kohanim can go to the מקוה.
mikvah. So it's telling you when does רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi blinking
of an eye occur? It occurs after רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda three-quarters
of a mil, after רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda 14 minutes. Okay, so
כהנים טובלים בו. kohanim tovlin bo. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא,
peshita, now to me that's not פשיטא peshita at all, who knows
when... but anyway, the גמרא Gemara always assumed it was obvious that
that's when
it occurred. No, מהו דתימא אימא בין השמשות דרבי יוסי משך שייכא
בדרבי יהודה. mahu deteima eima bein hashmashot de-Rabbi Yossi mishech shaycha beder-Rabbi
Yehuda. רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi blinking of the eye occurs somewhere in
the middle of רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda period. קא משמע לן Ka
mashma lan that that's not true, דשלים בין השמשות דרבי יהודה. deshalim
bein hashmashot de-Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot
is over, a full 14 whatever three-quarters of a mil is done
and that was full day according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi והדר
מותביה בין השמשות דרבי יוסי ve-hadar motveih bein hashmashot de-Rabbi Yossi and
then for that split second is a split second בין השמשות Bein
Hashmashot for רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbah Bar Bar Channah Amar Rabbi Yochanan. So
by the way, the most מחמיר machmir position of this גמרא Gemara
is sunset for three-quarters of a mil is בין השמשות. Bein Hashmashot.
The other positions are a half a mil, that's shorter. And then
there's another opinion of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, which is three-quarters of
a mil his total is definite day. So the most מחמיר machmir
position of all of these is from sunset till three-quarters of a
mil is בין השמשות. Bein Hashmashot. Before that is definite day, after
that is definite night. And according to this גמרא Gemara again if
it weren't for the גמרא Gemara in פסחים, Pesachim, if it weren't
for רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, you would say 14 minutes, maybe 18
minutes after sunset is definite night.
Meaning three-quarters of a mil.
Three-quarters of a mil, that is the most מחמיר machmir position. Okay,
the בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot ends and it's night. Right, the other
two positions we have is either half a mil or yes 18
minutes after is night but בין השמשות Bein Hashmashot until then it
was day. 14 whatever three-quarters of a mil, it was a split
blinking of an eye. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי יהודה
לענין שבת. Amar Rabbah Bar Bar Channah Amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke-Rabbi
Yehuda le'inyan Shabbat. We rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda for שבת.
Shabbat. Okay. Three quarters of a מיל *mil*, והלכה כרבי יוסי לענין
תרומה *v'halakha k'Rabbi Yosi l'inyan terumah*. We rule like רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yosi* for תרומה *terumah*. So what does this mean? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says בשלמא הלכה halacha כרבי יהודה לענין שבת, Shabbat לחומרא
*bishlama halakha k'Rabbi Yehuda l'inyan Shabbos, l'chumra*. I understand we rule like
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* for שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, לחומרא *l'chumra*. That means
that we're being strict. As I said, it means that we start
שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos* at sunset, right? Because that might be the because
that's when בין השמשות bein hashmashot, *bein hashmashot* begins, and we don't
end שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* till after בין השמשות bein hashmashot *bein hashmashot*.
אבל לענין תרומה מאי *aval l'inyan terumah mai*? What do you mean
for תרומה *terumah* we go like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*? You hear
the tape? No, it's the heat, it's just the heat. What do
you mean? אילימא *eileima*, if it is for טבילה *tvila*, that כהנים
*Kohanim* can go to the מקוה *mikveh*, the scenario we're discussing before
until רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*'s בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*,
why can you be lenient?
וכי *v'chi*? Why can you be lenient for טבילה *tvila*? That's still
a דאורייתא *d'Oraita*, it should have to be definitely during the day.
אלא לאכילת תרומה *ela l'achilat terumah*. It means that for when it
comes to eating תרומה *terumah*, דלא אכלי כהנים תרומה עד דשלים בין
השמשות דרבי יוסי *d'lo achli Kohanim terumah ad d'shalam bein hashmashot d'Rabbi
Yosi*. That the כהנים *Kohanim* cannot eat תרומה *terumah* until רבי יוסי
*Rabbi Yosi*'s בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* is over, which means what? It
means basically it means we're strict at the beginning, we're strict at
the end. We're strict at the beginning that שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos* begins
right at sunset,
which is what רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says, the more strict reading
of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, and restrict like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*
that שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* doesn't end, or to take another example, you
can't eat תרומה *terumah* until not only רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s three
quarters of a מיל *mil* is over, but you've also waited the
blinking of the eye of רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*, the extra second,
and now it's definitely the end and now you can eat תרומה
*terumah* and now שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos* is over you can do מלאכה
melacha *melacha*. So תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* asks the obvious question which is,
well first there's two questions. Why do you have to switch cases
from שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos* to תרומה *terumah*? Just say we're, you know,
we're strict at the beginning of שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, we're strict at
the end of שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*. So for that תוספות *Tosafot* says,
no, we wanted to point out that even though תרומה *terumah* was
lighter than שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*, we're going to be strict when it
comes to תרומה *terumah* as well, not just strict for שבת Shabbat
*Shabbos* issues, even strict for תרומה *terumah* which is, you know, it's
דאורייתא *d'Oraita*, but anyway תרומה בזמן הזה *terumah b'zman hazeh* maybe not,
anyway it's not as strict, even so, even for not as weighty
things we're strict with בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*. Fine. But why, תוספות
*Tosafot* says the better question is, why do you have to tell
me this whole thing for a split second? So תוספות *Tosafot* says
maybe there's some question when רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*'s split second occurs.
Maybe it doesn't occur literally the split second after רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda*'s three quarters of a מיל *mil*, maybe it occurs a few
minutes afterwards. Why would you say that? So to explain this גמרא
Gemara
*Gemara* based on other גמרות *Gemaras*, I don't know, based on other
גמרות *Gemaras*. So anyway, but whatever it is, basically according to this
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, we're just always
strict with בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*, but basically, but as we've seen,
it really is no more than from sunset until three quarters of
a מיל *mil*. You want to add a few extra minutes, fine.
From sunset 20 minutes, that's what you would come out from this
גמרא *Gemara*, you know, but not more. And as I said, the
other opinions come either from the גמרא *Gemara* in פסחים *Pesachim* or
from adjusting based on location in the globe. Let's see as the
גמרא *Gemara* continues. אמר רב יהודה Rav Yehuda, אמר שמואל *Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel*. So that was all תנאים *Tannaim*. Now we have
a new teaching of רב יהודה אמר שמואל *Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel*,
which is the following, a different way of determining בין השמשות *bein
hashmashot* of a space. כוכב אחד יום *kochav echad yom*, one star
is still day. שנים בין השמשות *shnayim bein hashmashot*, two stars is
בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*. שלשה לילה *shlosha layla*, as soon as you
can see three stars it's night. Now I don't know, a star
during the day is pretty hard, I mean, sometimes you can see
stars at the beginning of the day, the morning star which isn't
a star, it's Venus. But you know, to say that it's still
day, that sounds a little bit consistent with the opinion that even
after sunset it might still be day for a few minutes. Has
anybody ever seen stars before sunset? Mmm-hmm. Yeah? You can see stars
sometimes before sunset? It's only right before. Okay, but right before, but
you can. Yeah. Oh okay, all right. So anyway, תניא נמי הכי
*tanya nami hachi*. No, but I think they were planets. Yeah, I
was going to say. That could be, but the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't
distinguish. כוכבי לכת *kochvei lechet* or, you know, plant, anyway. Venus is
a planet. Right. Morning star is Venus, right. תניא נמי הכי *tanya
nami hachi*, similarly. כוכב אחד יום *kochav echad yom*, one star is
day, שנים בין השמשות *shnayim bein hashmashot*, two stars are בין השמשות
*bein hashmashot*, שלשה לילה *shlosha layla*, three are night. אמר רבי יוסי
לא כוכבים גדולים הנראים ביום ולא כוכבים קטנים שאין נראים אלא בלילה
אלא בינונים *Amar Rabbi Yosi lo kochavim gedolim hanirim bayom v'lo kochavim
ktanim she'ein nirim ela balayla ela beinonim*, not huge stars which are,
you know, which are seen often in the day and not the
tiny stars which are only seen like later at night, אלא בינונים
*ela beinonim*, average stars, three average stars. Now what's average? So as
I said, that's why our position of 42 minutes, 45 minutes is
basically when astronomers have said that stars are visible across the whole
sort of horizon, not horizon, the sky, and therefore we assume if
there's stars all across the sky we have at least three average
stars. But you imagine in the time of the גמרא *Gemara*, we
already have a full buy-in of looking towards the east, we're going
to have in a minute too. I mean the גמרא *Gemara* did
not say oh 42 minutes let me check my watch, you know.
What they did is they went outside, they looked, they saw three
stars, they did מלאכה melacha *melacha*. So but it is interesting that
now we are having a very different measure than before, and maybe
exactly for that reason that before there was not, you know, it
was harder to determine. It's reddish, darkish, how dark, whatever, it was
hard to pinpoint that, you know. And this is something that you
could just look up in the sky and know, oh, I can
see stars, it's already night. Yeah. This is weird, it looks like
רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* the תנא *Tanna* is explaining רב יהודה ושמואל
*Rav Yehuda v'Shmuel* the אמוראים *Amoraim*. So, no, because first of all
some say אמר רבי יוסי בר אבין *amar Rabbi Yosi bar Avin*.
And this is switch the גרסא *girsa*, and some, but the other
thing is it's תניא נמי הכי *tanya nami hachi*, we're quoting a
ברייתא *baraita* right now. Oh. So we started with a statement of
שמואל *Shmuel* and רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*, we're quoting a ברייתא *baraita*.
This position also appears in the in the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* as well
I should mention. Okay. One
main reason why we have these things is because, you know, if
it's a cloudy day you're not going to see so many stars,
so then maybe that's why you want another measure about it being
red.
That's true. And the גמרא *Gemara* will talk about that. So there
are different ways. But the first measure by the way, when the
גמרא *Gemara* quantified it, it became easier. But before it was quantified,
oh, no longer red it's now dark or whatever, that's a harder
type of a measure to use. So this might be where this
other measure comes up. The problem is as we've seen is what
happens when the measures don't exactly correspond. Okay. אמר רבי יוסי בר
אבין *Amar Rabbi Yose bar Avin*: העושה מלאכה melacha בשני בין השמשות
חייב חטאת ממנפשך *Ha-oseh melacha bi-shnei bein hashmashot chayav chatat mi-manafshach*. If
somebody does מלאכה melacha *melacha* Friday during the בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*
period and Saturday night during the בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* period, then
you definitely have transgressed שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* and you're חייב חטאת *chayav
chatat* if you've done it obviously not intentionally.
But only one חטאת *chatat*.
Right. Right. אמר ליה רבא לשמעיה *Amar lei Rava l'Shmaya*. Now, why
is this? So because one of them had to be night. But
the point is it's not really true, right? Because it depends when
you did בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*. Let's say בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*
is from six to 6:20. And let's say on Friday I did
מלאכה melacha. *melacha* at 6:05 and on Saturday night I did מלאכה
melacha *melacha* at 6:15. It's possible I did not do any מלאכה
melacha *melacha*, right? It's possible that night occurred at 6:10. So even
though six to 6:20 is בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*, maybe 6:10 was
night. So I got it I beat it at both ends. So
therefore רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosfos*, רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says and
תוספות *Tosfos* sort of agrees, that here what we mean is you
did מלאכה melacha *melacha* throughout the בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*. From six
to 6:20 straight on Friday and on Saturday night. So therefore even
if בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* was the last minute, night was the
last minute on Friday, 6:20, but that meant that I was doing
מלאכה melacha *melacha* on Saturday night. Or even if night was the
first minute at 6:00 and I wasn't doing מלאכה *melacha* Saturday night
but I was doing מלאכה *melacha* on Friday. So they say we're
talking that you did it straight through. The גמרא *Gemara* doesn't say
that and it does raise sort of interesting questions because you remember
the גמרא *Gemara* yesterday about a זב *zav* who's seen twice and
he's seen three times, exactly figuring that issue out about whether when
we think about בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*, here's the conceptual question and
I'm not going to unpack this right now, but it it ties
into this גמרא *Gemara* and the גמרא *Gemara* by זב *zav*. When
we think about בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*, this let's say 15 minutes
or whatever 20 minutes, six to 6:20, are we saying somewhere in
there is where night switches today, we just don't know where that
point is, right? It's somewhere in this 20 minutes, we just can't
pinpoint it. Or is it no, actually this whole period is by
definition נישט היי נישט היי *nisht hei nisht hai*, right? This by
definition is a quasi-night quasi-day period. It's not like night begins somewhere
and we don't know where, it's that by definition this is a
mixture of night and day. And therefore it has both the חומרות
*chumras* of night and the חומרות *chumras* of the day, but not
because we don't know the minute that it begins. So it's possible
to read it that way
and then that leads to questions about reading this, you know, whether
you have to assume here you did מלאכה *melacha* straight through the
entire period or not. But the general assumption of רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
תוספות *Tosfos* is more the first thing I said, that somewhere in
there is where the transition happens, we don't know how to pinpoint
it, so if you want to say you definitely are חייב חטאת
*chayav chatat*, it would only be when you did מלאכה *melacha* straight
through. But an alternative read is that no, it's not about pinpointing,
it's by definition this is a mixed type of a period. It's
dusk, and dusk by definition is this quasi-day quasi-night. Yeah, you got
it.
You just covered what I was going to ask.
All right, perfect. So now the גמרא *Gemara* continues. Now we get
more to trying to identify it. Okay. אמר ליה רבא לשמעיה *Amar
lei Rava l'Shmaya*: רבא *Rava* said to his attendant, אתון *atun*, you,
דלא קיימ לכו בשיעורי דרבנן *d'lo kaim-lehu b'shiurei d'rabbanan*, you're not so
good with the rabbinic times and exactly knowing how to translate those,
so let me give you a time you can use, you can
go by. עד דשמשא אריש דיקלי *Ad de-shimsha rei-sh diklei*, when the
sun is by the top of the palm trees, אתלו שרגא *at-lu
shraga*,
that would be when you should light a candle, you should stop
doing מלאכה *melacha* then because it's going to set very
soon. ביומא דעיבנא מאי *B'yoma d'imeina mai*? How about on a cloudy
day where you can't see it? במתא *B'mata*, so in the city,
חזי תרנגולא *chazei tarnagola*. You'll see that
the rooster will then sort of like move to the to the
to the coop maybe or get on the get on the fence.
רש"י *Rashi* says: היושבים על הכוש מבעוד יום *Hayoshvim al hakosh mi-bod
yom*. רש"י *Rashi* so like so it sounds like you know they
will when the day's about to be over they'll maybe be sitting
on the fence. בדברא *B'dabra*, and in the field, עורבי *orvei*. You
will see the ravens returning to their nest or coming back and
then you know it's about to be nightfall. אינמי *Inami* אדני *adanei*,
or this type of a grass called אדני *adanei*, which would sort
of sort of move towards the west, lean towards the west as
it was about to be nightfall. Now the funny thing about this
is you don't know the שיעור shiur *shiur*, we're not talking about
when night starts, we're talking about when בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* is
over, we're talking about
when בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* begins. When does בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*...
sunset. Who needs to be בקי בשיעורי דרבנן? Look out and see
if it's sunset or not. So, you know, so maybe it means
that you're in a place where there are mountains and you can't
see the sunset well and you know you're surrounded by palm trees
so you can see the sun at the top of the palm
trees but you can't see it when it goes down. Anyway that's
a little bit strange why you have to give a שיעור for
the beginning of שבת Shabbat if it's based on sunset. So this
leads some to suggest, even if you want to get another opinion
about בין השמשות, that when the גמרא says it starts at sunset
it doesn't mean sunset, it actually means before sunset. So anyway just
to confuse things more, but it is strange that the גמרא has
to give an alternative to just looking at the sunset, right? So
but anyway but this is actually the other point that's important about
this though is it is mentioning this period of time pre-sunset where
you stop doing מלאכה and where you light a candle. Now again
lighting a candle might just be the idea of it's the last
מלאכה you do, but it also is beginning to associate candle lighting
with the very שבת Shabbat. beginning right afterwards. And that all taking
place a period of time before sunset which obviously begins to translate
into our practice of you know lighting candles 18 minutes before and
then welcoming in the שבת. Shabbat, In ירושלים Yerushalayim they do 40
minutes and so on. Yes.
So if you're in the top of a mountain looking at the
sunset out to the west,
yes,
you're
not it didn't mention you at the top of the mountain. Mentioned
that the sun was at the top of the trees.
Right, I know what you're saying, you just look out and see
if the sunset.
Right, so it could be that it gets under the curvature of
the sky and it's not really the horizon.
Right, it could be the normal sunset at sea level is going
to be earlier than the sunset up on the top of the
mountain.
No, if you're at the top of the mountain and then you'll
actually what looks to you sunset will actually be after sunset at
sea level. That's exactly right, yes. Right, so it could be, yes,
so that's also the question also what when we say sunset do
we mean observable sunset, do we mean astronomical sunset, and what looks
like sunset depends on where you are. So that might be why
the גמרא is giving these times of giving you a few minutes
clearly as long as the sun's on top of the palm trees
it's not below sea level, so you're safe and therefore so that
could be why you're given these times. Okay, yes.
Did we use this phrase in terms of when to דאוון daven
נעילה? Neilah? Sun is the top of the palm trees. You ever
hear that? Top of the trees? You ever hear that?
Oh, might be but I'm not recalling it right now. Okay, so
let's take a look now now we move to a now we're
done with the technical issues of בין השמשות which has huge you
know implications every single שבת Shabbat if not more, you know for
הלכה and I gave you some of the the range of opinions.
Now we move to a to a way in which they brought
in שבת. Shabbat. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan:
שש תקיעות תוקעין ערב שבת. Shesh tekiot tokin erev Shabbat. They blow
the שופר shofar six times on ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. Presumably in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I don't know, maybe through all of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash? Well, but but that stone... Right,
right, exactly.
Didn't they put
on
the sirens in ירושלים Yerushalayim now?
Right, right, right, we learned about that in מידות. Middot. A place
where they... Right, right, right, מקום התקיעה. makom hatkiah.
I showed you that when we were doing מידות. Middot.
So they blow the sirens in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Right, in ירושלים Yerushalayim they blow a siren. So six blows. ראשונה
להבטיל את העם ממלאכה שבשדות. Rishona l'havtil et ha'am mimelacha shebasadot. The
first one to tell people you know to come in from the
field because it takes time to move in from the fields to
the city and people have to bring back their hoes and their
implements and all those things. So that's you know a good while
before שבת Shabbat to give them all time to come in from
the field. שנייה להבטיל עיר וחנויות. Shniya l'havtil ir v'chanuyot. To stop
the מלאכה being done in the city like the manufacturing מלאכה and
the stores, to get the stores to close up, the commerce. Okay,
that would be closer to שבת. Shabbat, I mean people still need
time to you know to transition but they're right in the city
so that's closer to שבת.
Is there a third in the field?
No, someone coming out to the field and blowing a שופר? shofar?
No, presumably, yeah, that's a good question. How could you hear it
everywhere? Was it like the lighting of the bonfires? One person lit
and then everybody repeated it? Yeah, it's not exactly clear how the
noise spread and got that far. שלישית להדליק את הנר. Shlishit l'hadlik
et haner. The third one, now you've given people everybody time, everybody's
hopefully home, and now the third one להדליק את הנר. l'hadlik et
haner. Now you light candles again candles as being the last thing
you do. But now you begin to see how candle lighting becomes
to be associated with the bringing in of שבת and this sort
of and you know is as if the act of candles brings
in שבת. Here talking about stopping doing the last מלאכה.
Okay, what are the other three for?
Wait one
minute. דברי רבי נתן. Divrei Rabbi Natan. That's what Rabbi Natan says.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה הנשיא אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
Hanasi omer, excuse me, רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi says: שלישית
לחלוץ תפילין. Shlishit lachlotz tefillin. The third one is taking off your
תפילין tefillin because you they would wear תפילין tefillin all day but
you can't wear תפילין tefillin when it gets to be night. Gets
a little funny because you couldn't wear תפילין tefillin at night any
day of the week. There's a special reason also you can't wear
תפילין tefillin on שבת, so that's so no, no, because also שבת
is אות, ot, so you know it's not it's not זמן תפילין.
zman tefillin. Anyway not exactly clear why he overemphasized that. Also not
clear according to him when he would when they light the candle.
רש״י Rashi says at the fourth תקיעה, tekiah, it's not spelled out
here. ושהה כדי צליית דג קטן. V'sha'ah k'dei tzliyat dag katan. You
wait the time it takes to fry a small fish. A few
minutes, או כדי להדביק פת בתנור, o kedei lehadbik pat batanur, the
time it takes to stick the bread to the oven, and רש"י
says and get a crust, because remember, by שבת you can only
put the bread in the oven if it will get a crust
before שבת begins. So presumably, so that, so there's enough time just
to do that. And then בתוקע מריע ותוקע, batokea meria vitokea, then
you do תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, tekiah teruah tekiah, which are your last
three, ושובת, veshovet, and then it's שבת. So the last three are
really all one new thing. Now it's שבת, but you do three
to make a very, you know, clear announcement שבת has now begun.
There's also a question when it mentioned the first three, whether it
was also תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, tekiah teruah tekiah, was it תקיעה תקיעה
תקיעה? tekiah tekiah tekiah?
And the last three are תקיעה תרועה תקיעה. tekiah teruah tekiah. Little
debate of רש"י, תוספות. Anyway, then it becomes שבת.
And they do anything, you know, at the other end, once it's
מוצאי שבת?
motzei Shabbat? No, it doesn't say that. אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, so that's very nice, you know, the
whole way the city, the community as a whole is moving towards
שבת and acknowledges, you know, you have to sort of, the steps
you have to do and be, and you know, and not at
the last minute wake up. So you know, שבת, and it's very
beautiful if that really sort of regulates the life of the city.
אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, מה נעשה
לבבליים? ma na'aseh leBavliyim?
That's all very nice, but what about the Babylonians? שתוקעים ומריעים, shetokim
umari'im, that they do the last, when they do the end תקיעות,
tekiot, they do תקיעה תרועה, tekiah teruah, ושובתים מתוך מריע, veshovtim mitoch
meria, and they stop doing מלאכה at the middle of the תרועה.
teruah. So presumably he's bothered that it wasn't תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, tekiah
teruah tekiah, and presumably he's bothered that they sort of stop during
this and not after it, which is, like, what is it? A
difference of a second? Anyway, but that was their מנהג, minhag, not
exactly, not what we just said. So הגמרא hagimara says, first הגמרא
hagimara says, תוקעים ומריעים, tokim umari'im, הוו להו חמשא. havu lehu chamsha.
One minute, if you only did תקיעה תרועה tekiah teruah at the
end, then it's three plus two, it's five. So presumably the, meaning
the בבליים Bavliyim presumably
didn't argue with the six. אלא שתוקע וחוזר ותוקע ומריע ושובת. ela
shetokea vechozer vetokea umaria veshovet. Okay, so they do תקיעה, tekiah, then
they do תקיעה תרועה, tekiah teruah, ושובתים מתוך מריע, veshovtim mitoch meria,
and they end in the middle of the תרועה. teruah. So anyway,
what about the בבליים? Bavliyim? They have a different practice. They don't
do תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, tekiah teruah tekiah, they do תקיעה תקיעה תרועה,
tekiah tekiah teruah, and they, they don't, they stop in the middle
of the תרועה, teruah, they don't stop after it. Why is it
such a big, I have no idea. מנהג אבותיהם בידיהם. minhag avoteihem
beyadeihem. All right, so they're doing what's their practice. Again, very strange,
right? It's like, who, you know, it's all just an arbitrary way,
and it's not like they're wait, it's not like they're doing מלאכה
too late. They're stopping a little bit earlier. I don't really understand
what the big, what the big workup is. I do want to
say though, we had that phrase before, if you remember, in the
context of lighting candles, right? ומה נעשה להם לבבליים, uma na'aseh lahem
leBavliyim, when the position said you could only use olive oil. I
forget if it was רב שמעון בן גמליאל, Rav Shimon ben Gamliel,
but somebody got up and said, oh, that's all very nice, you
want people only to do the olive oil, but what about the
Babylonians that don't, that only have this oil and these people only
have that oil? So that was a nice phrase. I forget if
that was רב שמעון בן גמליאל Rav Shimon ben Gamliel or who
it was that said it. Oh, here it was. רבי יוחנן בן
נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, מה יעשו אנשי בבל? ma ya'asu anshei
Bavel? מה יעשו אנשי מדי? ma ya'asu anshei Madai? But here it's
different because here presumably it's the בבליים Bavliyim in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, not
in בבל. Bavel. But right, presumably he's speaking about the fact that
the בבליים Bavliyim he sees, because we have no record that in
בבל Bavel they did the תקיעה תרועה תקיעה. tekiah teruah tekiah. So
it might be different than the, than the case before. Okay, anyway,
let's take a
look. הגמרא hagimara says like this. מתני
ליה רב יהודה לרב יצחק בריה.
matni lei
Rav Yehuda leRav Yitzchak bereih. So רב יהודה, when he taught this
over to רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, his son, here's what he said.
שנייה להדליק את הנר. shniya lehadlik et haner. Not the third one
for lighting candles, by the second one already when people are packing
up their stores you light candles. סימן. siman. Who's that like? לא
כרבי נתן ולא כרבי יהודה. lo keRabbi Natan velo keRabbi Yehuda. רבי
יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, it's not like רבי נתן Rabbi Natan
who says the third, it's not like רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi who didn't tell us when you light candles, but presumably it
wasn't earlier. אלא שלישית להדליק את הנר. ela shlishit lehadlik et haner.
Fine, he didn't say two, he said the third one you light
the candle. כמאן? keman? כרבי נתן. keRabbi Natan. Like רבי נתן Rabbi
Natan who said the third one you light the candle. תנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל. tana dbei Rabbi Yishmael. We find out from the house
of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. שש תקיעות תוקעין ערב שבת. sheish tekiot
tokin erev Shabbat. Six תקיעות. tekiot. התחיל לתקוע תקיעה ראשונה. hitchil litkoa
tekiah rishona. When they began the first תקיעה, tekiah, נמנעו העומדים בשדה
מלדור מלחרש מלעשות כל מלאכה. nimnu ha'omdim basadeh milador milacharosh mila'asot kol
melacha. So so far it's similar, it's just being said in a
different, different way. שבשדה. shebasadeh. The people out in the field stopped
hoeing and what do you call it? Making furrows and doing all
the מלאכה in the field. ואין הקרובים. ve'ein hakerovim. Now we add
a little color. ואין הקרובים רשאים להיכנס עד שיבואו רחוקים ויכנסו כולם
כאחד. ve'ein hakerovim rishaim lehikanes ad sheyavo'u rechokim veyikanesu kulam ke'echad.
So you have people working different degrees outside of the city. The
ones closer to the city cannot start coming in until the ones
further out get together, you know, move closer in and then they
all come together as a group. Why is this? So I thought
maybe it had to do with, you know, you don't want to
leave them stranded in the field. It's dangerous, they'll be alone, you
know, it's getting to be nightfall. But if that were true, it
would be true during the rest of the week as well and
more true during the rest of the week when it was really
dark when they came home. So רש"י says it was that people
should not be suspicious and say oh, we saw other people coming
back a few minutes ago. Why are you coming back ten minutes
later? Probably you were still doing מלאכה after the siren went off.
So in order that people shouldn't think bad of you, you all
come back together. Okay, I know you like that. ועדיין חנויות פתוחות.
ve'adayin chanuyot petuchot. And after the, after the... And after the first
one still the stores were open והתריסים מונחים *V'hatrisim munachim* and the
תריס *tris* like the shutters were placed because they would like take
down the shutters of the doors and they'd put them in front
of them like a table, you know, put them on stands and
put them as a table to put their wares. So people were
still doing business out in the market, people were still in the
factories in the city. התחיל לתקוע תקיעה שניה *Hitchil litkoa tkiya shniya*,
the second תקיעה *tkiya* began, נסתלקו התריסים *nistalku hatrisim*,
so they took away the, you know, the shutters, they locked up
the stores, they pulled down the metal gates וננעלו החנויות *v'nin'alu hachanuyot*,
they locked up the doors and all the מלאכה *melacha* in the
city stopped. ועדיין *V'adayin*
I wanted to say something in addition to what's being added here
in addition to the color is it says התחיל לתקוע *hitchil litkoa*,
התחיל לתקוע *hitchil litkoa*, which makes it sound like it was a
the first תקיעה *tkiya* maybe lasted for a good few minutes, you
know, like the process which took, you know, cause it wasn't just
they did the first תקיעה *tkiya* and this is what happened, but
they began it, which could also explain the position before about the
בבליים *Bavliyim*, like maybe these things took a few minutes each blast
and that's a little bit.
See my question on רש"י *Rashi* is
let's just wait because we're going to get to some more... Okay.
ועדיין חמין מונחים על גבי כירה *V'adayin chamin munachim al gabei kira*,
but okay, still your hot stuff, it was ערב שבת *erev Shabbat*,
you didn't want to take the stuff off the fire until the
last minute. So the hot water was still on the oven וקדירות
מונחות על גבי כירה *v'kdirot munachot al gabei kira* and the pots
were still on the oven. התחיל לתקוע תקיעה שלישית *Hitchil litkoa tkiya
shlishit*, the third תקיעה *tkiya* began, then you have to take all
the stuff off the fire, סילק המסלק *silak hamasilak*, you took the
hot water off the fire that you're just going to leave off
the fire והטמין המטמין *v'hitmin hamatmin*, the stuff that you were going
to keep in, sort of, you know, you'd bury it in sort
of like in towels and other things to keep it warm for
tomorrow, you did the הטמנה *hatmana*, you sort of, you know, put
it in the heat preserving material והדליק המדליק *v'hidlik hamadlik* and you
lit the candle and now guy the last minute stuff has to
be done now ושהה כדי לצלות דג קטן *V'shaha k'dei litzlot dag
katan*, okay, או כדי להדביק פת בתנור *o k'dei lehadbik pat b'tanur*
or the bread in the oven ותוקע ומריע ותוקע *v'tokeia umaria v'tokeia*,
תקיעה תרועה תקיעה *tkiya truah tkiya* ושובת *v'shovet* and you are שובת
*shovet*. Notice here by the way lighting the candle is not the
only thing mentioned and it's not like the ritual of beginning שבת
*Shabbat*, it's like you take the food off the fire, you turn
on the lights and so on. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא *Amar
Rabi Yossi b'Rabi Chanina*, שמעתי *shamati*, I heard שבא להדליק אחר שש
תקיעות *sheba lehadlik achar shesh tkiot*, if you actually you're running late
on שבת *Shabbat*, never would happen to any of us, and you
need after the six תקיעות *tkiot* are done and you still haven't
lit your candle מדליק *madlik*, you can still light for like a
minute or two after why שהרי נתנו חכמים שיעור לחזן הכנסת להוליך
שופרו לביתו *sheharei natnu chachamim shiur l'chazan haknesset leholich shofaro l'beito* because
it's really not שבת *Shabbat* even then because the guy who blew
the שופר *shofar*, he has to take the שופר *shofar* home. So
so therefore you really have a minute or two afterwards. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says אמר לו *amar lo*, they said to him אם
כן נתת דבריך לשיעורין *im ken natata dvarecha l'shiurin*, no then it's
too flexible, where's his home, close or near, that's what רש"י *Rashi*
says, not only where's his home close or near but you're undermining
the whole point if you tell people after this you've got a
few minutes then everybody's going to make their own decision when the
time is, no don't do that, אלא *ela*, what about the answer
how does the guy bring his שופר *shofar* home מקום צנוע יש
לו לחזן הכנסת בראש גגו *Makom tzanua yesh lo l'chazan haknesset b'rosh
gago*, he's got a secret place on the on the roof ששם
מניח שופרו *shesham maniach shofaro*, that's where he puts his שופר *shofar*
לפי *L'fi* and this is where we'll end here שאין מטלטלין לא
את השופר ולא את החצוצרות *she'ein metaltelin lo et hashofar v'lo et
hachatzotzrot*, you cannot carry the שופר *shofar* or חצוצרות *chatzotzrot* on שבת
*Shabbat* even if it's not carrying without an עירוב *eruv* just because
of a מוקצה *muktzah* problem and we will continue with this discussion
tomorrow.
But the piece you feel, right?